Guide to the Christopher D'Arcangelo Papers MSS.264
Fales Library and Special Collections
Christopher D'Arcangelo Papers
1965-2003
1975-1978
Fales Library and Special Collections
D'Arcangelo, Christopher
MSS.264
9 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 box binder, 1 record carton, and 3 flat-file folders.
Biographical Note
Christopher D'Arcangelo, an artist working during the 1970's, was born in 1955 and died in 1979. In 1975 he performed unauthorized pieces at New York's Whitney Museum, Museum of Modern Art, Guggenheim Museum, and the Metropolitan Museum, and in 1976 at the Norton Simon Museum in Pasadena, CA. In January 1977, LAICA published his proposal "LAICA as an Alternative to Museums". Christopher was also a carpenter and contractor, and in September of 1977 he began work on functional constructions. During 1978 he performed unauthorized pieces at the Louvre in Paris and the Rosa Esman Gallery in New York City. Christopher also took part in an exhibition at Artists Space in New York City in 1978; from 1976 until his death, he was working on a proposal for the Van Abbe Museum in Eindhoven.
Scope and Content note
This collection is comprised of materials created and compiled by Christopher D'Arcangelo in the course of his work as an artist and as an assistant to other artists, and includes correspondence, notes, receipts, photographs, floorplans, and objects. The collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Work Files consists of subject files kept by D'Arcangelo for projects he executed or hoped to execute, and files for projects he worked on with or for other artists. The latter include documentation of Daniel Buren's "Ballets" from 1977 and 1978.
Series II: Posthumous Files consists of documents that were collected by D'Arcangelo's executors after his death, including correspondence and articles. Subseries A contains files documenting the Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, an exhibition held at Algus Greenspon Gallery in October 2011. Researchers who had accessed the Christopher D'Arcangelo Papers at the Fales Library were invited to respond to his work and their experiences working with D'Arcangelo's Papers. Exhibition attendees were also invited to respond.
Series III: Objects includes key artifacts D'Arcangelo used in his art pieces.
Series IV: Media consists of video, audio, and film elements. Access copies may not be available for research use at this time.
Arrangement
Folder titles reflect D'Arcangelo's original titles. Small changes were made to facilitate access. The collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Missing Title
Series I: Work Files
Series II: Posthumous Files
Series III: Objects
Series IV: Media
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
The collection was donated to Fales by Cathy Weiner and the D'Arcangelo Family Partnership in 2009.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Periodicals; Correspondence.; Articles.; Financial records; Notebooks; Posters.; Conceptual art.; Photographic prints.; Sketchbooks.; Artifacts.; Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Whitney Museum of American Art; Norton Simon Museum (Pasadena, Calif.); Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art; Musée du Louvre; D'Arcangelo, Christopher; Lawler, Louise; Buren, Daniel; Esman, Rosa; Artists Space (Gallery); Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Los Angeles County Museum of Art; Stedelijk Van Abbemuseum; Antonakos, Stephen, 1926-2013; J. Paul Getty Museum; D'Arcangelo, Allan, 1930-1998
- Series I: Work Files, 1965-1979
  - Announcement/P. Nadin [Functional Constructions], 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Antonakos Ceiling - Contract, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antonakos Paperwork for Ceiling, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Artists Space, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Artists Space - Catalogs and Postcards, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Artists Space - Reference, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Artists Space - Wall Text, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ballet #9 [Daniel Buren], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bell and Howell Projector and Camera, undated; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Buren Ballet #8, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Buren Ballet #10, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Buren Ballet #11, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Buren Ballet #12, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Buren Ballet #13, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Buren Ballet #14, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Buren Ballet #15, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Buren Ballet #16 14th St NYC, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Buren Ballet #17 Flower District, Flatiron District, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Buren Ballet #18 The Empire State Building, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Daniel Buren - Catalogs, Photos, Postcards, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Buren - Ballets - Reference, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Buren Parade, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Contemporary Arts Center [Cincinatti], May 20, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jeffrey Deitch Shows/John Weber Gallery, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Eindhoven - Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rosa Esman - Door, June 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rosa Esman - Look Out for What You Look At, May 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rosa Esman Invitational - Text, June 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Functional Constructions, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Functional Constructions - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Art Reference, 1975-1977; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Getty Museum - Reference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Guggenheim Museum, NY, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hands Locations, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Harper Painting, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jobs Billed, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kunst Des XX. Jahrunderts Aus Dem Van Abbemuseum Eindhoven - Catalog, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - LAICA Journal, No. 13, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Louise Lawler - Ceiling, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Lives" Catalog - Jeffrey Deitch, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Louvre, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Louvre - Writings + Statement, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mad Magazine Cover, July 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Museum, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Monchengladbach Grant, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Movie Camera Brochures, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated; 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Scrapbook, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Norton Simon Museum, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Paint Charts, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - P.S. 1, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rijksmuseum / Rembrant / Restoration, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook/Notebook, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Statue of Liberty Brochures, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Van Abbemuseum, Eindhoven, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Van Abbemuseum - Writing, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Whitney Postcards, Statement, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Writing statements by Cathy Weiner, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    General
    Created at request of D'Arcangelo, these documents record what Cathy Weiner witnessed during the 1975 pieces at the Whitney Museum of American Art, The Museum of Modern Art, and the Guggenheim Museum.
  - Work Binder A (Box A)
    Binder A is a similar recreation of the binder that D'Arcangelo created to document his artmaking; it was assembled by the D'Arcangelo Family Partnership.
  - Work Binder B (Box B)
    Binder B is a partial recreation of the binder that D'Arcangelo created to document his artmaking, as well as other documents assembled by the D'Arcangelo Family Partnership.
- Series II: Posthumous Files, 1978-1998
  - Subseries A: General
    - Articles about D'Arcangelo, 1991, 1996, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Articles/Reviews, 1979; undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chronologies and Inventories, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Inlcudes Christopher D'Arcangelo Chronology, created by Gideon D'Arcangelo 1993, updated 2009.
    - Copies of D'Arcangelo Notebook, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Copies of Work, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence about D'Arcangelo Works, 1979, 1988, 1992, 1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Greene Naftali, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Bruce Hainley, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Journal: Southern California Art Magazine No. 23, June-July 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - List of Cathy Weiner's photographs of D'Arcangelo Work, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Oehlen Williams 95 Catalog, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Recent works and notes on six series - Peter Nadin, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Subseries B: Algus Greenspon Homage
    Scope and Content
    This subseries contains files documenting the Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, an exhibition held at Algus Greenspon Gallery in October 2011. Researchers who had accessed the Christopher D'Arcangelo Papers at the Fales Library were invited to respond to his work and their experiences working with D'Arcangelo's Papers. Exhibition attendees were also invited to respond.
    - Breslin, David: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Greenspon, Algus: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage - Responses from Binder, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Greenspon, Algus: Christopher D'Arcangelo: Letters to Contributors, Installations, Exhibition List, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Sanders, Jay: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage from Blue Binder, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Garcia-Torres, Mario: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Hainley, Bruce: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Harris, Larissa: Moratorium, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Macgregor, Dean: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Press: Christopher D'Arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series III: Objects
  - Stamp ("When I state that I am an anarchist, I must also state that I am not an anarchist") (Box 5, Object ID: 264.2.0001)
  - Stamp ("When I state that I am an anarchist,") (Box 5, Object ID: 264.2.0002)
  - Handcuffs with key (Box 5, Object ID: 264.2.0003)
  - Handcuffs with keys in Box (Box 5, Object ID: 264.2.0004)
  - Coin changer (Box 5, Object ID: 264.2.0005)
  - Box of Functional Constructions flyers (Box 5)
- Series IV: Media
  - Subseries A: Audio - Access Copies
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
    - Interview with Louise Lawler, 1993; ID: 264.0021 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0021)
      Format: CD-R
      Source: ID: 264.0016 "Christopher D'Arcangelo CD #3"
      Content:
      Interview with Louise Lawler conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo at 401 Greenwich Street #8; 1/15/1993
    - Interview with Daniel Buren, undated; ID: 264.0022 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0022)
      Interview with Daniel Buren conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo at 45 Lispenard Street.
    - [1] -- Cathy and Allan Suite, 1992; ID: 264.0023 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0023)
      Source: ID: 264.0017 "Christopher D'Arcangelo CD #2"
      Commentary about Chris's films by Cathy Weiner, Allan D'Arcangelo, and Gideon D'Arcangelo; 11/21/92
    - [1]-- Cathy and Allan [2]-- Cathy Suite 2 [3]-- Cathy Suite, [1992]; ID: 264.0024 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0024)
      Commentary about Chris's films by Cathy Weiner, Allan D'Arcangelo, and Gideon D'Arcangelo
    - Interview with Cathy Weiner, pt. 2, 1992; ID: 264.0025 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0025)
      Conversation between Cathy Weiner and Gideon D'Arcangelo about Chris D'Arcangelo's work. Interview conducted at 202 Front Street; 10/21/1992
    - Chris, unknown; ID: 264.0026 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0026)
      Source: ID: 264.0018 "Christopher D'Arcangelo CD #1"
    - Ballet #17, Two Chairs, undated; ID: 264.0027 (Box Shared Fales 137, Cd 264.0027)
  - Subseries B: Audio - Originals
    - Ballet #17, August 28, 1978, Flower District, Fashion District, ID: 264.0010 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0010)
      Format: 1/4" audiocassette
      Duration: 00:30:00
    - Christopher, undated; ID: 264.0011 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0011)
      Duration: Unknown
    - Interview with Cathy Weiner and Allan D'Arcangelo, conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo, 11/21/92, 1992; ID: 264.0012 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0012)
    - Interview with Cathy Weiner and Allan D'Arcangelo, conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo, 11/21/92, 1992; ID: 264.0013 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0013)
    - Interview with Peter Nadin conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo on the subject of collaboration with Chris D'Arcangelo, 11/27/92, 1992; ID: 264.0028 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0028, Case 264.0028)
    - Interview with Louise Lawler conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo at 407 Greenwich St. #8, 1/15/93, 1993; ID: 264.0014 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0014)
    - Interview with Daniel Buren at 45 Lispenard St. 9W, conducted by Gideon D'Arcangelo concerning plans for project - the work of Chris D'Arcangelo, 4/25/93, 1993; ID: 264.0015 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0015)
    - [Two Chairs for Talking], undated; ID: 264.0009 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0009)
    - Christopher D'Arcangelo CD #1, undated; ID: 264.0018 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0018)
    - Christopher D'Arcangelo CD #2, undated; ID: 264.0017 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0017)
    - Christopher D'Arcangelo CD #3, undated; ID: 264.0016 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0016)
  - Subseries C: Video - Access Copies
    - Christopher D'Arcangelo: Museum Pieces and Other Footage, unknown; ID: 264.0019 (Box Shared Fales 137, Dvd 264.0019A, Dvd 264.0019B)
      1. Guggenheim Museum, NYC #3 2. Metropolitan Museum of Art, NYC #4 3. Norton Simon Museum, LA #5 4. Whitney Museum, NYC #1 5. Museum of Modern Art, (Guernica) NYC
      The original VHS recording 264.0007, which has been digitized, includes three additional segments: "Filmed at Home," "Stencils on Fire" and "Suitcase Piece."
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      DVDs transfered from VHS original 264.0007. The video footage is silent.
  - Subseries D: Video - Originals
    - Christopher D'Arcangelo: Museum Pieces and Other Footage, unknown; ID: 264.0007 (Box 6, Vhs ID: 264.0007)
      Scope and Contents
      Contents: 1. Guggenheim Museum, NYC #3 2. Metropolitan Museum of Art, NYC #4 3. Norton Simon Museum, LA #5 4. Whitney Museum, NYC #1 5. Filmed at home, Amsterdam Ave and 98th 6. Stencils on Fire - Riverside Park Panels 12/74 #2 7. Museum of Modern Art, (Guernica) NYC 8. Suitcase Piece
      DVD access copies 264.0019A and 264.0019B contain additional information on interstitial labels, although they do not include "Filmed at Home," "Stencils on Fire" and "Suitcase Piece."
      Duration: 41 minutes.
    - Chris - Events, undated; ID: 264.0008 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0008)
      Format: VHS
      Duration: 00:41:00
  - Subseries E: Film - Access Copies
    Access copies are currently unavailable to researchers.
  - Subseries F: Film - Originals
    - Film from Whitney 1/31/75: "When I State..." Whitney Modern 786 Amsterdam, 1975; ID: 264.0002 (Case 264.0002)
      Format: Super 8mm
    - 7/8/76 Norton Simon Pasadena, 1976; ID: 264.0003 (Case 264.0003)
    - Suitcase, 786 Amsterdam, undated; ID: 264.0001 (Case 264.0001)
    - Guggenheim and Met, 1975; ID: 264.0004 (Case 264.0004)
    - Cathy Weiner - Film Reel B, undated; ID: 264.0005 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0005)
    - Cathy Weiner - Film Reel A, undated; ID: 264.0006 (Box 6, Media ID: 264.0006)
- Oversize - Series I: Work Files
  - Viva Mao; Viva Anarchism; When I State That I am an Anarchist - stencils, undated (Box 9)
    Used stencils rehoused by the Library's perservation lab; two stencils could not be unrolled. Researcher access is limited.
  - Four Texts, for Artists Space - printer's acetate, undated (Box 9)
  - When I state that I am an anarchist..., undated (Folder 3 Left)
  - Diazotype Floorplans, undated (Folder 2)
  - "Thirty days Work-long version" and "The idea that today there is no aesthetic...", undated (Folder 3)
  - Thirty days work, undated (Box Shared Fales 080, Folder 5)
  - "We all do things in our own little way. Long Live anarchism.", undated (Folder 3 Right)
  - "Long Live Anarchism", undated (Box Shared Fales 080, Folder 4)
    Used stencil
  - Floorplans and Maps, undated (Box Shared Fales 080, Folder 3)
- Oversize - Series II: Posthumous Files
  - Artforum, April 2003 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Documents sur l'art [magazine], 2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Garcia Torres, Mario: Christopher D'arcangelo Homage, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Institute for Art and Urban Resources, undated (Folder 4)